Texas Council of Church-Related Colleges records, Inclusive: 1937-1982, undated, Bulk: 1973-1980
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
Texas Council of Church-Related Colleges records
Inclusive: 1937-1982, undated, Bulk: 1973-1980
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
713
Texas Council of Church-Related Colleges, 1937 - 1981
4 document boxes.
The collection includes member institution files, administrative files, and financial records of the Texas Council of Church-Related Colleges (1937-1981).
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
The Texas Council of Church-Related Colleges (TCCRC) was founded in 1937 during a meeting at Baylor University. Its stated purpose was to “give emphasis to the fundamental place of religion in education,” and specifically to promote the mutual needs of and cooperation between church-related colleges in Texas. Representatives of fifteen senior and junior colleges were present at the TCCRC’s first meeting, though its early membership included some twenty-nine Texas colleges.
Throughout its existence, the TCCRC served as a forum for communication between administrators from church-related colleges across Texas. Though not a particularly active organization, the TCCRC’s annual meetings attracted national speakers and dozens of local college presidents and deans. These meetings featured addresses and roundtables relevant to the common issues faced by these administrators: financial shortfalls, denominational relations, community involvement, legal questions, and the like.
Over time, however, other Texas-based organizations such as the Independent Colleges and Universities of Texas (ICUT) began to form more active but less religious alternatives to the TCCRC. Finally, in 1981, the TCCRC was dissolved following recommendations from Baylor’s president, Abner McCall. McCall suggested that the TCCRC had to “devise a program which would mean something and deal with value education,” or else simplify the schedules of administrators by disbanding and leaving its work to the ICUT. The group’s members decided on June 4, 1981, and voted unanimously to dissolve the TCCRC.
Scope and Content
This collection was acquired by gift, in three parts, from past officers of and administrators related to the Texas Council of Church-Related Colleges (TCCRC). The first gift came in 1974 from Alton B. Lee, a past president of the TCCRC and Baylor’s dean of admissions. This gift consisted of two bound volumes of minutes, which are found at the beginning of Series II. The second and largest gift, comprising the majority of Series II and the entirety of Series I and Series III, was given in 1982 by J. Paul Savell. Savell was the secretary of the TCCRC and the academic dean of what was then Southwestern Assemblies of God College (Waxahachie, TX). A final gift of miscellaneous materials, located at the end of Series II, was offered in 1984 by James Berryhill, who was then serving in Baylor’s Academic Advisement office. The materials are in good condition.
The contents of the first and third series, I. Member Institution Files and III. Financial Documents, were mostly produced during the 1970s, the final decade of the TCCRC’s existence. The first series is largely comprised of correspondence between the TCCRC’s officers and the administrators of its member institutions. Most of these documents relate to annual meetings and the payment of dues. The third and final series includes bank statements, ledgers, paid checks, and check stubs, which cumulatively provide a detailed picture of the TCCRC’s financial affairs.
This collection’s middle and largest series is II. Administrative Files. This series is also the most chronologically diverse. While most of its contents were likewise produced during the 1970s, it also includes annual meeting materials dating to the 1960s and annual meeting minutes dating back to the group’s founding in 1937. Beyond annual-meeting-related documents, this series also contains a copy of the TCCRC’s constitution, a list of its past presidents, correspondence, and various printed materials.
Arrangement
Prior to current processing, this collection’s contents were either loose or arranged in roughly-titled acidic folders. The member institution files were arranged alphabetically, the annual meeting materials were ordered chronologically, and most of the financial documents (particularly the bank statements) were grouped and rubber-banded by year. A rough initial inventory reflects this same organization.
These previous orderings have largely been preserved in the present round of processing, with only minor corrections to alphabetization and chronology. The materials have also been refoldered and retitled, and are now arranged into three series: I. Member Institution Files, II. Administrative Files, and III. Financial Documents.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 713. Acquired 1974-06-10
Index Terms
Subjects (Organizations)
Texas Council of Church-Related Colleges -- Records and correspondence.
Subjects
Christian universities and colleges -- Texas -- Societies, etc.
Genres
Constitutions.; Financial records.; Financial statements.; Minutes (Records); Pamphlets.
- Member Institution Files, 1973-1980, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  This series is largely comprised of correspondence between the officers of the Texas Council of Church-Related Colleges (TCCRC) and the administrators of its member institutions. Most of the documents relate to the planning of annual meetings, the payment of dues, or the TCCRC's scholarship certificate program. The series is in good condition.
  - Abilene Christian College (Abilene, Texas), 1974-1979 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Arlington Baptist College (Arlington, Texas), 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Austin College (Sherman, Texas), 1974-1979 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Baylor University (Waco, Texas), 1973-1979 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bishop College (Dallas, Texas), 1974-1979 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Concordia Lutheran College (Austin, Texas), 1974-1979 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Criswell Center for Biblical Studies (Dallas, Texas), 1977-1979 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Dallas Baptist College (Dallas, Texas), 1974-1979 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Dallas Bible College (Dallas, Texas), 1974-1979 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Dominican College (Houston, Texas), 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - East Texas Baptist College (Marshall, Texas), 1974-1979 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Gulf Coast Bible College (Houston, Texas), 1974-1979 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Hardin-Simmons University (Abilene, Texas), 1974-1979 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Houston Baptist College (Houston, Texas), 1974-1980 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Howard Payne University (Brownwood, Texas), 1974-1979 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Huston-Tillotson College (Austin, Texas), 1974-1979 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Incarnate Word College (San Antonio, Texas), 1974-1979 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Jacksonville College (Jacksonville, Texas), 1974-1979 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Jarvis Christian College (Hawkins, Texas), 1974-1979 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Lon Morris College (Jacksonville, Texas), 1974-1979 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Lubbock Christian College (Lubbock, Texas), 1974-1980 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - McMurry College (Abilene, Texas), 1974-1979 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Our Lady of the Lake University (San Antonio, Texas), 1974-1979 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Saint Edward’s University (Austin, Texas), 1974-1979 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Saint Mary’s University (San Antonio, Texas), 1974-1979 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Schreiner College (Kerrville, Texas), 1974-1979 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Southern Bible College (Houston, Texas), 1974-1979 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Southern Methodist University (Dallas, Texas), 1973-1979 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Southwestern Assemblies of God College (Waxahachie, Texas), 1974-1979 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Southwestern Union College (Keene, Texas), 1977-1979 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Southwestern University (Georgetown, Texas), 1974-1979 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Texas Christian University (Fort Worth, Texas), 1974-1979 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Texas College (Tyler, Texas), 1974-1979, undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Texas Lutheran College (Seguin, Texas), 1974-1979 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Texas Wesleyan College (Fort Worth, Texas), 1974-1979 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Trinity University (San Antonio, Texas), 1974-1980 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - University of Dallas (Irving, Texas), 1974-1979 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - University of Mary Hardin-Baylor (Belton, Texas), 1974-1979 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - University of Saint Thomas (Houston, Texas), 1974-1979 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Wayland Baptist College (Plainview, Texas), 1974-1979 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Wiley College (Marshall, Texas), 1973-1979 (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Administrative Files, 1937-1982, undated; 2
  Most of the documents in this series are related to the annual meetings of the Texas Council of Church-Related Colleges. They include meeting minutes, correspondence, pamphlets, budget reports, and a variety of other printed materials. This series is in good condition.
  - Annual Meeting Minutes: First Twenty Annual Meetings, 1937-1960 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Annual Meeting Minutes: Second Era of Annual Meetings, 1961-1973 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Annual Meeting Minutes, 1961-1973 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Annual Meeting Minutes, 1973-1977 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Annual Meeting Materials (1939 February 17-18, 1950 November 21-22, 1952 November 25-26, and 1963 April 4), 1939-1963 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Annual Meeting Materials, 1963 April 4 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Annual Meeting Materials, 1964 April 9 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Annual Meeting Materials (1965 April 8), 1965-1966 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Annual Meeting Materials, 1967 April 6 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Annual Meeting Materials (1969 April 10), 1969-1970 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Annual Meeting Materials, 1970 April 2 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Annual Meeting Materials, 1973 April 1 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Annual Meeting Materials (1974 April 3-4), 1974 April, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Annual Meeting Materials (1975 April 2-3), 1974-1975, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Annual Meeting Materials (1976 March 31), 1976 March-April (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Annual Meeting Materials (1977 March 30), 1977 March-April, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Annual Meeting Materials, 1978 March 29 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Annual Meeting Materials, 1979 March 28 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Annual Meeting Materials, 1980 April 9 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Annual Meeting Materials (1981 April 1) (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Annual Meeting Materials (1981 April 1), 1981-1982, undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Special Meeting Materials (1981 June 4), 1981 May-July (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Constitution of the Texas Council of Church-Related Colleges, circa 1957, undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Past Presidents of the Texas Council of Church-Related Colleges, circa 1979 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Texas Council of Church-Related Colleges: Annual Meeting Materials, Correspondence, Pamphlets, and Magazine (1 of 4), circa 1960-1973, undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Texas Council of Church-Related Colleges: Annual Meeting Materials, Correspondence, Pamphlets, and Magazine (2 of 4), circa 1960-1973, undated (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Texas Council of Church-Related Colleges: Annual Meeting Materials, Correspondence, Pamphlets, and Magazine (3 of 4), circa 1960-1973, undated (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Texas Council of Church-Related Colleges: Annual Meeting Materials, Correspondence, Pamphlets, and Magazine (4 of 4), circa 1960-1973, undated (Box 3, Folder 25)
- Financial Documents, 1960-1980, undated; 3
  This series is comprised of financial documents from the Texas Council of Church-Related College's last two decades, including check stubs, bank statements, and ledgers. The series is in good condition.
  - Baylor University: President’s Associates Brochure, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Texas Council of Church-Related Colleges: Bank Statements and Paid Checks, 1973-1974 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Texas Council of Church-Related Colleges: Bank Statements and Paid Checks, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Texas Council of Church-Related Colleges: Bank Statements and Paid Checks, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Texas Council of Church-Related Colleges: Bank Statements and Paid Checks, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Texas Council of Church-Related Colleges: Bank Statements and Paid Checks, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Texas Council of Church-Related Colleges: Bank Statements and Paid Checks, 1979-1980 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Texas Council of Church-Related Colleges: Check Stubs and Receipts, 1970-1973 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Texas Council of Church-Related Colleges: Check Stubs and Receipts, 1974-1975 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Texas Council of Church-Related Colleges: Check Stubs and Receipts, 1976-1978 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Texas Council of Church-Related Colleges: Dues Structure, undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Texas Council of Church-Related Colleges: Ledger, 1960-1979 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Texas Council of Church-Related Colleges: Ledger and Annual Meeting Materials, 1976-1980 (Box 4, Folder 13)